All right, everyone. We are back. Uh
slight technical difficulty, but uh
we're back and we are good to go. So
again, just put a one in the chat if uh
you could hear me. Uh put a two in the
chat if you are ready. We have prayed.
I'm going to go ahead and pray again. Um
and uh and then we're going to start
this message. So let's do that now.
Heavenly Father, again we ask for your
presence to be with us as we go through
your word. Please Lord speak as our
prayer in Jesus name.
Amen. Daniel chapter 8 and verse
14. Uh that will be the focus of our
study today. And we're going to begin
just by simply reading
uh the eth chapter of Daniel. We're
going to break it down a little bit. Um
just I there's one thing I want to just
point out before we get into breaking
down that chapter and uh it'll be a
slight interruption if you will right
after verse one but it's going to be a
very important point. So we'll do that.
We're going to read through Daniel 8 and
then we're going to go back and begin to
methodically break down this chapter,
the context of the chapter and uh and
see from the Bible what Daniel chapter 8
is actually talking about. So let's go
ahead and begin. We're going to go to
Daniel chapter 8 and verse 1. Daniel
chapter 8 and verse one. The Bible says
here, "In the third year of the reign of
King
Belshazar, a vision appeared unto me,
even unto me Daniel after that which
appeared unto me at the first. And I saw
in a vision. And it came to pass when I
saw that I was at Shushan in the palace,
which is in the province of Elum. And I
saw in a vision, and I was by the river
Uli.
Um, we're gonna pause here for a moment
because I want to point out
that even though Daniel is currently in
the the the kingdom of Babylon, that's
the present ruling kingdom, the Bible
actually goes out of its way to point
out that in this vision,
Daniel was at
Shushan in the palace.
He was at Shushan in the
palace. Now, how many of you have have
read the book of Daniel chapter 8
before? Just put a one in the chat if
you have read this chapter
before. Probably one of the things that
you may have never paid attention to is
the fact that Daniel in this vision is
at
Shushan in the
palace, which is very interesting. And
let me share with you why.
because
Shushan was
actually the the
capital of the Grecian
Empire. So, so for example, we see in
Nehemiah 1 verse one the words of
Nehemiah the son of Hakaleia. And it
came to pass in the month of Shisloo in
the 20th year as I was in Shushan the
palace. Now, why is this significant?
Because Susan is the place which
represented the reign of the Meo Persian
Empire.
Meaning Daniel in
vision is
taken to a place that signifies the
future rule of the Meo Persian
Empire. So let's go back.
Let's keep watching. Let's keep looking.
Um the Bible tells us here Daniel 8:3
and verse4. Then I lift lifted up mine
eyes and saw and behold there stood
before the river a
ram which had two horns. And the two
horns were high, but one was higher than
the other. And the higher came up um the
higher uh came up last. And I saw the
ram pushing westward and northward and
southward so that no beast might stand
before him. Neither was there any that
could deliver out of his hand. But he
did according to his will and became
great.
And as I was considering, behold, a
hegoat came from the west of the face on
the face of the whole earth, and touched
not the ground. And the goat had a
notable horn between his
eyes. And he came to the ram which had
the two horns, which I had seen standing
before the river, and ran unto him in
the fury of his
power. Verse seven. And I saw him come
close unto the ram, and he was moved
with colar against him, and smokeote the
ram, and break his two horns. And there
was no power in the ram to stand before
him, but he cast him to the ground and
stamped upon him, and there was none
that could deliver the ram out of his
hand. Verse verse 8, the Bible says,
"Therefore the the hegoat waxed very
great, and when he was strong, the great
horn was broken, and for it came up four
notable ones towards the four winds of
heavens.
And out of one of them came forth a
little horn which waxed exceeding great
toward the south and toward the east and
toward the pleasant
land. And it waxed great even to the
host of heaven. And it cast down some of
the host or the stars to the ground and
stamped upon them. Yay, he magnified
himself even to the prince of the host.
And by him the daily sacrifice was taken
away and the place of his sanctuary was
cast down. Verse 12 and
13. And the host was given him against
the daily sacrifice by reason of
transgression, and it cast down the
truth to the ground, and it practiced,
and it prospered. And then comes a
question. Then I heard one saint
speaking, and another saint um said unto
the certain saint which spake, How long
shall be the vision concerning the daily
sacrifice and the transgression of
desolation to give both the sanctuary
and the host to be trotten underfoot?
And he said unto me, unto 2,300 days,
then shall the sanctuary be cleansed.
All
right. So, here is the context. Here is
the the the the full reading at least up
until this vision is is is uh uh brought
to this point of 2300 days, then shall
the sanctuary be cleansed. And the
question is, what does this vision mean?
What is this time period? How should we
interpret this time period?
Um, to do this, to understand what's
going on in Daniel chapter
8, we really need to see a larger
picture. We need to understand the
context of the entire book of Daniel.
So, let me say it this way. If you
isolate Daniel chapter 8 from the rest
of the book of Daniel, you're already in
trouble. You're already in trouble.
So, so what needs to happen is we need
to get a big picture of what's going on
in the book of Daniel. Now, in the book
of Daniel, there are uh
five visions. You'll see it up on the
screen here. In the book of Daniel,
there are five visions. And these
visions take place in Daniel chapter 2,
Daniel chapter 7, Daniel chapter 8,
Daniel chapter 9, and then Daniel 11 and
12 is one vision. Even though it's
divided by a chapter, the one vision
spans Daniel 11 and concludes in Daniel
12. It's the same vision or the same uh
uh prophecy, if you will. So, uh uh in
order to to understand Daniel 8 is right
in the center of the of the of the book
of Daniel, it's right in the center of
the five visions. So what I want to do
is just run briefly through the vision
of Daniel 2 7 9 11 and 12. Now we're not
going to go through in great detail. I
just want to show you something very
significant. So in Daniel 2 uh we have a
vision of a man um made of different
metals and we know that that man is a
symbol of the kingdoms according to the
book of Daniel chapter 2. So the head of
gold is Babylon. The the uh chest and
and arms of silver is Meo Persia. The
belly and thighs of brass is Greece. And
then the legs of Rome, the legs
represent the kingdom of Rome. A and
then uh the Bible tells us that a stone
is cut out without hands that destroys
the image on its feet. So notice with me
Daniel chapter 2 verse 44. And as the as
the as Daniel is giving the
interpretation of this dream, he says um
in the days of these kings. So we're
talking about the 10 toes in which the
the stone that is cut out of the
mountain without hands destroys the
image in in the toes. It says in the
days of these kings shall the God of
heaven set up a kingdom which shall
never be destroyed. And the kingdom
shall not be left to other people, but
it shall break in pieces and shall
consume all these kingdoms. and it shall
stand forever. For as much as thou
sawest the stone that was cut out of the
mountain without hands, and that it
break in pieces the iron, the brass, the
clay, the silver, and the gold, the
great God has made known to the king
what shall come to pass hereafter, and
the dream is certain, and the
interpretation thereof is sure.
So in Daniel chapter
2, we have a vision that
spans thousands of years.
Please put that in the chat for
me. The vision spans, if I would ask you
how long is this vision, you would say
the vision spans thousands of years and
it it climaxes with the second coming of
Jesus. It climaxes with something
something
universal. It's a huge thing, right?
It's a it's a big
deal. The kingdom of heaven is being set
up
It is like a universal event. So y'all
put a one in the chat if you're
following so far. That's all we're doing
in Daniel 2. We're seeing that this
vision spans thousands of years and it
climaxes not with something little, not
with something small, but with something
huge. It climaxes with with heavenly
events. The second coming of Jesus. All
right, let's go to Daniel chapter 7. Now
in Daniel chapter 7, the second of the
five visions, we have a vision of
animals. Daniel sees a lion followed by
a bear followed by a leopard which has
four heads followed by a fourth
nondescript beast with seven with 10
horns. And then the t horns we we we see
parallels the 10 toes of Daniel 2. Then
after the ten horns rises a little horn.
Now I want you to note how the prophecy
of Daniel chapter 7
concludes. Um in Daniel 7:9 the Bible
says I beheld till thrones were cast
down and the ancient of days did sit
whose garment was white as snow and the
hair of his head like the pure wool. His
throne was like the fiery flame and his
wheels as burning fire. A fiery stream
issued and came forth from before him.
Thousand thousands ministered unto him,
and 10,000 times 10,000 stood before
him. The judgment was set and the books
were open. I beheld them because of the
voice of the great words which the horn
spake. Talking about the little horn of
Daniel 7, I beheld even till the beast
was slain and his body destroyed and
given to the burning flame. So, so, so
then it goes on to say, "And I saw the
night visions, and behold, one like the
Son of Man came with the clouds of
heaven and came to the ancient of days,
and they brought him near before him.
And there was given him dominion and
glory, and a kingdom, that all people,
nations, and languages should serve him.
His dominion is an everlasting dominion,
which shall not pass away, and his
kingdom that which shall not be
destroyed." So in Daniel chapter 7, this
vision also concludes in a grand
climactic
way. This vision also spans thousands of
years from the time of Babylon all the
way to the destruction of this beast.
And in fact, you might ask, when is this
beast body given to the burning? Let's
go back to the screen and we will notice
in Revelation chapter
19:1 the Bible says, "I saw heaven open
and behold a white horse and he that sat
on him was called faithful and true and
in righteousness he judge and make war."
This is a description of the second
coming. Just a few verses down, it says,
"And I saw the beast and the kings of
the earth and their armies." Almost like
this verse is is combining Daniel 2, the
kings of the earth. Daniel 7, the beast
and their armies gathered together to
make war against him that sat on the
horse and against his army. And the
beast was taken, and with him the false
prophet that wrought miracles before
him, which he de which with which he
deceived them that received the mark of
the beast, and them that worshiped his
image. These both were cast alive into a
lake of fire burning with brimstone. So
then what do we see? What do we see from
the vision in Daniel chapter 7? We see
that the vision also spans thousands of
years. We see that the vision also ends
in a grand climactic
way. Doesn't end with a little event. It
ends with something that is
universal. Y'all put a one in the chat
if you're following so far.
Now, we're going to skip Daniel 8 cuz
that's a chapter that we want to study,
but we're going to skip Daniel 8 for a
moment and we're going to go to Daniel
chapter 9. Now, in Daniel chapter 9,
Daniel receives a vision regarding the
the coming of Jesus. I want you to note
how all of these visions so far, Daniel
2, Daniel 7, and now Daniel 9, all
revolve around the person of Jesus
Christ.
Daniel chapter 7 gives us a view of the
first coming of Jesus. But hold on,
please note with me verse
25, which says, "Know therefore and
understand that from the going forth of
the command to restore and to build
Jerusalem unto the Messiah, the prince
shall be three score in two weeks. The
street shall be built again, and the
wall even in troubleous time." Now
notice verse 26. And after three score
and two weeks shall Messiah be cut off,
but not for himself. And the people of
the prince that shall come shall destroy
the city and the sanctuary. Now watch
this. And the end thereof shall be with
a flood. And unto the end of the war
desolations are
determined. Notice verse
27. And he shall confirm the covenant
with many for one week. And in the midst
of the week he shall cause a sacrifice
and oblations to cease. and for the
overspreading of abominations he shall
make it desolate even until the
consummation and that determined shall
be poured out upon the desolate. What is
the consummation? The consummation is
the end of all
things. I want you to note how Jesus
speaks of the abomination of desolation
in Matthew 24:14. Matthew
24:15. The Bible says, "When you shall
therefore see the abomination of
desolation spoken of by Daniel the
prophet, stand in the holy place. Whoso
readeth, let him understand." And it
goes on to talk about all these things
that are going to happen. And it points
to the end of time. And then just a few
verses later, it says, "Except those
days shall be shortened, there shall be
no flesh be saved, but for the elect's
sake, those days shall be shortened.
Then if any man shall say unto you, lo,
here is Christ, or there, believe it
not. For there shall arise false Christs
and false prophets, and shall show great
signs and wonders, in so much that if it
were possible, they shall deceive the
very elect. Behold, I have told you
before, and then shall appear the sign
of the Son of Man in the heavens. So,
let's pause for for a second. We're not
even going to read the rest of this
verse. You're going to see the Son of
Man coming in the clouds. Daniel 9 not
only points to the first coming of Jesus
but it goes beyond that to the
consummation. So much so that even
futurist Christians Christians who
believe in a futurist uh prophetic view
take Daniel chapter 9 verse 27 to apply
to the last days. They believe the
antichrist will come and make a treaty
with Israel for seven years. You know
that you you
you've heard of this the left behind
series. It's all based on Daniel 9:27.
In other
words, even in Daniel 9, the vision of
Daniel 9
culminates with the second coming of
Jesus.
Y'all put a y'all put a five in the chat
if you understand what we're doing right
now. If you understand what we've done
so far, Dan, there are five visions in
the book of Daniel. We've seen that
vision number one is a grand vision. It
culminates with the second coming of
Jesus. Daniel chapter 7, the same thing.
It culminates with the second coming of
Jesus. We've skipped Daniel 8 and we're
just going to Daniel chapter 9. Daniel
chapter nine we've seen culminates it
points out not only the first coming of
Christ but it culminates with the
consummation the second coming of Jesus.
Jesus himself puts the abomination of
desolation not only in the days of Rome
but also
also at the very end of
time. So now let's go to Daniel 11 and
12. This is the very last vision of the
book of Daniel. Daniel 11 and 12. Uh,
and we're just going to note here in
Daniel 11, there's a conflict going on
between these two powers. One is the
king of the north, one is the king of
the south. It begins during the Meo
Persian Empire, but expands all the way
to Daniel 12:1, which reads this, "And
at that time shall Michael stand up, the
great prince, which standeth for the
children of thy people, and there shall
be a time of trouble such as never was
since there was a nation even to that
same time. And at that time thy people
shall be delivered. Everyone that shall
be found written in the book. And many
of them that sleep in the dust of the
earth shall awake, some to everlasting
life, and some to shame and everlasting
contempt. And they that be wise shall
shine as the brightness of the
firmament, and they that turn many to
righteousness as the stars forever and
ever. So what we have here in Daniel
11:12, the final vision, is that this
vision also ends in a very climactic
way. The climax of this vision, the the
the apex of this mission, the
culmination of this of this vision I
should say, is the second coming of
Jesus where the dead are
resurrected. Are we good so
far? So now please understand what we
have just
done. Please note with me on the screen.
Note with me on the screen. Remember, we
have skipped the vision of Daniel
chapter 8. I just want to show you that
in Daniel chapter 2, the climax, stone
smashes image, eternal kingdom is set
up. It's the second coming of Jesus
leads to the thousand years. In Daniel
7, same thing. You've got a judgment, a
heavenly judgment, culminates with the
second
coming, thousand years. Daniel 9ine, the
vision of Daniel 9, the same thing.
First coming of Jesus, his crucifixion,
desolations of the temple until the
consummation, the very end culminating
with the second coming. That's the end
of the war. That's the
culmination. Are you with me? Daniel 11
and 12, same
thing. Concludes, begins a meet of
Persia, concludes with the second
coming.
So what we what we should notice about
the grand theme of the book of Daniel is
that the
prophecies
climax or culminate with the second
coming of
Jesus. Are we
good? The visions are universal and the
visions all span thousands of years.
So now our question
is, will Daniel 8, will the vision of
Daniel
8 be any different? What do y'all think?
Will the vision of Daniel 8 be
different? In other words, will the
vision of Daniel 8 culminate with
something that was not so big? Will it
culminate with something that was not
global? will culminate with something
that
is that doesn't have to do with the
second coming of Jesus. What do you all
think? If there are five visions in the
book of Daniel and vision one, two,
vision four and five are all spanning
thousands of years and are all climactic
in the sense of they culminate with
something huge, something global.
What is the
likelihood that the vision in Daniel 8
will be
anticlimactic? Will be something small
and insignificant? The one right in the
center of the book of Daniel. What is
the sign? What is the the the likelihood
that the vision will be about something
that's just, you know,
local, not too big of a deal?
What do y'all
think? If you're saying that it is
probably likely that the vision of
Daniel
8 would be in the same context as the
rest of the book of Daniel, I would
agree with you. I would agree with you.
Let's go back to the book of Daniel,
chapter 8 now. And I want you to note
what the angel what Daniel says when the
angel is about to come and explain to
him. So he came near where I stood. And
when he came, I was afraid and fell upon
my face. But he said unto me,
"Understand, oh son of man, for at the
time of the end shall be the vision."
Isn't that
interesting? The angel that comes to
explain to Daniel this vision is
basically saying that the vision will
connect with the time of the end.
Verse 19, he said, "Behold, I will make
thee to know what shall be in the last
end of the indignation. For at the time
appointed, the end shall be." You guys,
right now, it would appear that Daniel
8, the vision of Daniel 8, whatever it
is, must have something to do with the
end
times. That's just right, right out the
box, right out the out of the gate. The
angel is literally saying, "Hey, this
vision, just like Daniel 2, just like
Daniel 7, just like Daniel 9, which you
will get in the future, just like Daniel
11 and 12, it is the it there is
harmony. Let's put it that
way. There is harmony between these
prophecies. And the only way you can get
Daniel 8 wrong is if you break the
harmony. is if you is if you disconnect
from the harmony of the book of Daniel.
Now remember I told you this is going to
be
methodical. This is going to be
surgical. But just because it's
methodical and surgical does not mean
that it's going to be
difficult. Now just let me see by a show
of hands how many of you get the the
line of reasoning or the logic that we
have just used without having yet
touched Daniel 8. We're simply seeing
that the five visions in Daniel all
conclude with the same
thing. They all conclude with the second
coming which grace would be connected
with the 1000 years. Even Daniel chapter
9. And even though we disagree with our
Christian friends about that last uh par
that last verse in Daniel chapter 9 that
it's about an antichrist in the future,
we do believe that the consummation is
at the end of time.
Daniel 8 tells us that the vision is at
the end. Now I want you to note
something else. Let's go back to the
book of Daniel chapter 8. And I want you
to notice again verse 13 and 14. So
there it says, "Then I heard one saint
speaking and another saint said unto
that certain saint which spake, how long
shall be the vision concerning the daily
sacrifice and the transgression of
desolation to give both the sanctuary
and the host to be trodden underfoot?
And he said unto me, "Unto 2,300 days,
then shall the sanctuary be cleansed."
Please note with me that the word here
uh for vision, shazam, um it literally
means a dream, a revelation, an oracle.
So the angel, listen.
Now, by the way, how many of you can
say, pastor, the point you just made
just now settles the question for me?
Just put a five in the chat, if if what
we just covered, just looking at the
context of all the prophecies of Daniel,
how many of you say to yourself, "Wow,
you know what? That one thing alone
helps me to know that Daniel chapter 8
must also be dealing
with thousands of
years, not 2300
days, but thousands of
years. We're going to prove it. If that
point is good enough for you, praise
God. But there's more to be proved.
There's there's more evidence that
demonstrates this. Let me show
you. Note the question again. Uh if you
have a King James vi Bible, you will see
that the word um
concerning is
italicized. It's italicized.
Meaning when we read how long shall be
the vision concerning the daily and the
transgression desolation to give both
the sanctuary and the host to be tried
underfoot. That word concerning is
italicized, meaning it's not in the
original
text. Now, that word concerning is
concerning. And here's
why. Because when people typically read
How long shall be the vision concerning
the daily
um the transgression of desolation,
they're focused on the little horn.
But that is the wrong focus of the
question. Now trust me, you're you
probably scratch your head like, "Wait,
what?" No, no,
no. Look carefully at the
question. The question, if you take out
the the italicized words, it would
simply read, "How long, the vision, the
daily, the transgression of desolation
to give both the sanctuary and the host
to be trod underfoot." So let's read a
couple let's read this in a couple
different translations.
How long shall the vision last
concerning the daily sacrifice and the
transgression that causes the
desolation? How long will the vision
be? Let's keep reading. How long shall
the vision
continue? How long will the things in
this vision
last? How long will the things in this
vision, the daily burnt offering, the
destruction, uh take place?
So what is the angel asking here? Let's
come back for a
moment. What is the angel asking
here? Daniel overhears the angel asking
how long not listen now. Not how long
does the little horn do his thing.
Y'all go
ahead and put a eight in the chat if you
understand the distinction that we just
made. The question is not how long will
the little horn do what he's doing. That
is not the question. Put a eight in the
chat if you understand what I'm saying.
The question is not how long will the
little horn do what he's doing. The
question
is how long is this
vision? Now I'm going to ask you to put
a nine in the
chat if you caught that just now.
The question is not how long will the
little horn do x y and z. That's part of
the question. But the actual question is
how long is this
vision? When we add the word concerning,
it's just
identifying the vision. How long is the
vision? You know, the one about the
little horn, the one about all the stuff
he's going to How long is his vision?
That's the question. How long is his
vision? So if the question is how long
is this vision? Then we got to ask
ourselves what does the vision
include? That's right, Robert. How what
is the duration of this vision? How long
is this vision? Well, what does the
vision include? Let's go back to the
screen and I want you to note with me
Daniel chapter 8. Daniel chapter 8 verse
21.
The angel begins to explain to
Daniel. And notice he doesn't start with
the little
horn. He starts at the beginning of the
vision. The ram which you saw having two
horns are the kings of Media and Persia.
Then the rough goat is the king of
Greece and the great horn that is
between his eyes is the first king. Do
y'all see
this? What Daniel 8 is telling us is
that the vision
spans the kingdom of Meor Persia. It
spans the kingdom of Greece and it and
it goes all the way to this little horn
power. Whatever this little horn power
is, we haven't identified it yet, but
whatever this little porn power is, we
know this little horn power must
continue to the second coming of
Jesus. Because if Daniel 8 is like
Daniel 2 or Daniel 7 or Daniel 9 or
Daniel
11, this little horn power and we will
see. Remember the angel said this
continues to the time of the end. So now
the question is how long is this vision
the one with the ram the hegoat the the
the great horn between his eyes the four
horns that break off in his place and
then the rise of this little horn. How
long is the vision? Not how long does
the little horn do how long is the
vision? So if division
begins in the kingdom of Meo Persia and
concludes kingdoms later then this 2300
years which is the answer to the
question how long the vision not how
long the little horn but how long the
vision concerning the little horn. The
vi that same vision concerns the ram and
the hegoat. And the angel that explains
this to Daniel verifies this by
beginning his explanation by talking
about the
ram. If the vision spans me, Persia and
Greece and then whatever comes after
that, this 2300 days must be what,
y'all?
What must the 2300 days be? If the 2300
days span the
vision, what must these 2300 days
be? Do 2,300 days can 2300 days
span the reign of the Meo Persian
Empire, the reign of the Grecian
Empire? No. Listen,
beloved, you don't need to go to Ezekiel
chapter 4. A day equals a year. You
don't need to go to Numbers chapter 14.
You No, you don't need to do any of
that.
No, just staying in the chapter.
Just staying in the
chapter and just noting the
question. How long shall be the vision?
Just stop right there. Everything else
is qualifying. How long shall be the
vision? How long shall be the vision?
What vision? Oh, the one you've just
come to explain to
me. And
beloved, it becomes absolutely clear
that this time period spans the entire
vision. Not just the little horn. It
spans the entire vision. Y'all go ahead
and I don't usually I usually stay from
1 to nine, but please go ahead and put a
10 in the chat if you have just like
this is
like pastor I got
it. Put a 10 in the chat. I usually
stick one to nine, but I'll tell you,
I'm so excited that I think this one I
think this is a
10. I think y'all need to put that 10 in
the chat.
So we now know that when the angel
begins to explain the vision, he starts
with the ram. By the way, the ram
represents, as we noted, the Meo Persian
Empire. Now,
now here is a question. How can
we how can we verify that these days
equal years? I think we've already seen
it and we've already seen it clearly.
But now there's additional information
for
us. To see this additional information,
we need to go to Daniel chapter 9. And
we're going to go to Daniel chapter 9.
And uh and we're going to begin um we're
going to begin with verse one. We're
going to begin with verse
one. So in Daniel chapter 9 verse one
and by the way we're going back to
Daniel 8. So just we're we're building
we're building. So in Daniel chapter 9
vers1 the Bible says in the first year
of Darius the son of Ahazeras the seed
of the Mes which was made king over the
realm of the Calaldanss. In the first
year of his reign, I Daniel understood
by books the number of the years whereof
the Lord, the word of the Lord, came to
Jeremiah the prophet, that he would
accomplish 70 years in the desolation of
Jerusalem. And I set my face unto the
Lord God to seek by prayer and
supplication with fasting and sackloth
and ashes. And I prayed unto the Lord my
God, and made my confession, and said,
'Oh Lord, the great and dreadful God,
keeping the covenant, and mercy to them
that love him. We have sinned and have
committed iniquity, and have done
wickedly, and have rebelled, even by
departing from the precepts and from thy
judgments. Now, let's pause for a
second. Let's pause for a second. And I
here's my question for you. Let's come
back for a moment. Why is Dan Why does
Daniel 9 open up this way? Why is Daniel
like I
understood I understood by the book of
Jeremiah the number of years Lord that
you said the sanctuary would lay
desolate. Why is Daniel opening up? Why
does Daniel 9 open up with Daniel saying
this?
Why? And what does that have to do with
the previous chapter? Let me show you.
Let's go back to the screen and I want
you to notice with me verse 17. Now
therefore, oh God, hear the prayer of
thy servant and his supplication, and
cause thy face to shine upon thy
sanctuary that is desolate for the
Lord's sake. Oh my God, incline thine
ear, and hear, open thine eyes, and
behold our desolations, and the city
which is called by thy name. For we do
not present our supplications before
thee for our righteousness, but for thy
great mercies. Oh Lord, hear, O Lord.
Forgive, oh Lord, hearken and do. Defer
not for thine own sake, oh my God, for
thy city and thy people are called by
thy name. All right. What's going on
here? Daniel is like, hold on,
Lord. I know according to
Jeremiah that you promised that we would
spend 70 years, the city and the temple
would lay desolate for 70 years and
then there would be a rebuilding. We
would get to go back. But what I just
saw in Daniel
8 has confused me. What do you mean unto
2300 days and then shall the sanctu
where where sanctuary be cleansed? If
that's 6 and 1/2 years, wait a minute,
Lord. Are you about to delay? What do
you mean like the temple isn't even
built yet? Is we haven't rebuilt it.
What are you talking about, God? I'm
confused here. I know what you said,
Lord. Are you saying that the temple
that is supposed to Are you saying that
this 70 years, which we are right upon
right
now, are you saying that that's not
going to happen anymore? Are you saying
that there's going to be a delay? All
right, y'all. Put in the chat, put a
five in the chat if you understand the
cont. If you understand now why Daniel
is praying with such ferveny, if you
understand now why Daniel is saying,
"Lord, please do not defer. Don't push
this back. Why is he praying that? Why
is he pleading? Why is he fasting?"
Because he's like, "Hold
on. Daniel A just threw me
off. We don't even have a sanctuary. But
we're still in Babylon. What do you
mean? Somebody's going to do this and
this and this to the temple and and and
the temple's going to be defiled and
under 2300 days then shall san what do
you
mean? And so Daniel comes to pray and
he's pleading that the Lord does not
defer. He's like, "Lord, we've sinned.
We've done wrong. I acknowledge it, but
please Lord, do not
defer. Do not defer.
So that's right, Nerky. Whether even in
Daniel's mind, if he's if he's if he's
thinking is this 2,300 days or years, I
don't understand. If he and let's give
him that. Let's say that he does not
understand at the
moment. Whether he understood or not,
he's coming and saying, is this being
deferred? Like why are we why what have
we done now? How have we gone wrong now?
Lord, whatever we've done, forgive
us. Why this extension?
And so now you know why the angel has
come to give him understanding. Y'all
put a five in the chat. Put a five in
the chat if you're like, "Oh, I get it."
Now you know why that because Daniel,
he's
thinking the
tabernacle, all this is going to happen
to this tabernacle.
And the angel is going to come to
explain. The angel is going to come to
explain so that just in case Daniel does
not understand this 2300 time period, he
will understand it by Daniel chapter
9. Watch what the angel
says. Daniel 9 verse
22. And he informed me and talked with
me and said, "Oh Daniel, I am now come
forth to give thee skill and
understanding. At the beginning of thy
supplication, the commandment came
forth, and I am come to show thee, for
thou art greatly beloved. Therefore,
understand the matter and
consider the vision." What
vision? The vision of Daniel chapter 8.
the vision of Daniel chapter
8. That's why he's
praying. I don't understand, Lord. Like,
what what have we done? What where have
we gone wrong again? Why this
delay? And then the angel begins to
explain the 70w week prophecy.
He
says 70 weeks are determined. That word
determined means cut off from. 70 weeks
are determined or cut off from
what? Cut off from a larger prophecy.
Cut off from a prophecy that came
previously.
70 weeks are determined upon thy people
and upon thy holy city to finish a
transgression to make an end of sins to
make reconciliation for iniquity and to
bring an everlasting righteousness to
seal up the vision and prophecy and to
anoint the most holy. And now note this.
Know therefore and understand that from
the going forth of the commandment to
restore and build
Jerusalem unto the Messiah the prince.
And then he gives this time period. Now
let's pause for a second.
There were four decrees that were
given re revolving around the rebuilding
of Jerusalem and the temple. And each
decree served a different purpose. So
number one, here's what we know. That
decree, whichever decree we choose, came
under the empire of the Meo Persians.
Who did the meopersians represent in
Daniel chapter 8? What was used to
represent the meopersians? The
ram. Isn't it doesn't it then make sense
why the vision begins with meersia.
The vision begins with me Persia in
Daniel 8 because that's the kingdom
that's going to give the
decree by which you start counting this
2300 day time period. That's why the
vision doesn't begin with Babylon. It
begins with Meo Persia. How long shall
be the vision?
2300 days. that 2300 days must span
these kingdoms beginning in the Meo
Persian Empire which coincidentally is
the kingdom that issued all four
decrees. So now we just got to ask
ourselves a question well which decree
which decree do we start counting from?
Now we know that this is it's got to be
years. Why? Because the 70 weeks in
Daniel chapter 9 is days of
years. Are y'all following me? So if the
70 weeks, if the 490 days is really 490
years, then the larger portion from
which it is taken from must also be
years. And we know that because Daniel
in his prayer is concerned about what he
saw in Daniel 8. That's why he's
praying. That's why he's fasting. He's
like, "Hold on. I know God when you said
that things were going to be rebuilt why
the delay." And the angel comes to
explain to
him in connection with Daniel chapter 8.
So which decree? Which decree? There
were four decrees given. Let's go to the
screen. There were four decrees given.
One was given by
Cyrus 538. The next was given by Darius.
The third was given by Artiserxes. And
the fourth also by artis Xerxes. The
first decree just built just dealt with
the rebuilding of the temple in
Jerusalem. The second decree was a
affirmation to continue building the
temple. The third decree is the one in
which the city is rebuilt, a civil
government is set up
and
and the laws of God are
enforced. And yes, Terry, you can't cut
off 490 years from six and a half years.
So which decree then do we count from?
Remember the prophecy said the prophecy
said know therefore and understand that
from the going forth and commandment to
restore and build not the temple but
Jerusalem the
city. The city had to be
rebuilt not the temple. So notice then
the first decree was just the temple.
The second decree also just the temple.
The third decree is found in the book of
Ezra. And watch what this decree says.
And thou, Ezra, after the wisdom of thy
God that is in thine hand, set
magistrates, set magistrates and judges,
which may judge all the people that are
beyond the river. All such as know thy
know the laws of thy God, and teach ye
them that know them not. So, so check
this out guys. It is when judges are set
up in
Jerusalem. It is that decree that fits
the beginning of the 400 the beginning
of the 2300 year prophecy. It is that
decree. Remember, if the 490 is cut off
from the 2300, which we've just seen
that it is, then they both start at the
same time. And note this. Why is God
starting the prophecy with a decree that
restores the law and judgment? The law
and judgment. Come on, y'all. Do not let
me get excited all by myself right now.
Why is God starting the 2300 day
prophecy with the restoration of law and
judges?
I want you to note with me Isaiah 1 26
which prophetically said this. And I
will restore thy judges as at the first
and thy counselors as at the beginning.
Afterward thou shalt be called the city
of righteousness, the faithful city.
What did God say he was going to do
through the prophet Isaiah? He's going
to restore to Jerusalem judges and
counselors. Now they've got their own
system. Now the laws of God are in place
and they have judges for judgment,
judges for judgment, and laws for
law. Why is God starting the 2300 day
prophecy with this uniting of law and
judgment?
In
fact, in
fact, the people come out of
Babylon, judgment is set
up for judicial and civil
authority, and God's law is
highlighted. Did y'all catch that?
How is a
2300 year prophecy going to
begin on a local
scale the same way it will culminate on
a global
scale. God's people coming out of
Babylon, a law being
restored, and judgment being set up.
You guys, you cannot make this stuff
up. You can't make this stuff
up. Revelation 14 7 and 8, I heard
another angel flying in the midst of
heaven. Verse 6, uh uh having the
everlasting gospel to preach unto them
that dwell on the earth to every nation,
kindred, tongue, and people, saying with
a loud voice, verse 7, fear God and give
glory to him, for the hour of his
judgment is come, and worship him that
made heaven, the earth, the sea, and the
fountains of water. And then verse
eight, there followed another angel
saying Babylon is fallen is fallen that
great city because she made all nations
drink of the wine of the wrath of her
fornication. What are the odds that
exactly what begins the 2300 years
coming out of
Babylon, the restoring of the law of
God, and judgment being set up. What are
the odds that those three things are
exactly what happens on a global
scale at the conclusion of the 2300 day
2300 year prophecy. It is almost as if
God is saying, "I'm reinstating
accountability and covenant justice
among my people. This is going to be the
beginning of a final and cosmic
judgment." Come on
y'all. Are y'all following so
far? We're not
done because we still have more to go.
But I need you. Y'all just put a 10 in
the chat if you're like, "Oh, but like
you're pastor. I see it. I get it. We're
looking at this thing from a thousand
different angles, y'all.
So then if you count from 457 BC and you
add 2300 years, beloved, that's what
brings you down to
1844. What's going to start happening in
1844, pastor? Are you saying that
judgment is going to begin in 1844? Are
you saying that a law is going to be
restored in 1844? Are you saying that
there's going to be a people coming out
of Babylon in 1844? No, I'm not saying
that. That's what prophecy is
saying. That's what prophecy is pointing
out. So now the question is now the
question is okay then well who is this
little horn power? So, so far we've seen
the context of Daniel shows that all the
prophecies including the prophecy in
Daniel 8 culminate with the second
coming of Jesus. Therefore, we've also
seen that the prophecy of Daniel 8
because the question is how long shall
be the
vision concerning the little horn? That
same vision has to do with the ram has
to do with the heiggoat that the 2300
days
spans the vision the entire vision. So
we've seen that the 2300 days must be
years. We we verify that because in
Daniel chapter nine, Daniel is praying,
Lord, I don't understand like you said
70 years we will be in desolation. And
if you're attacking on another 6 and a
half years or another 2,300 years, where
help me, let me fast. Let me pray. Lord,
help me to understand because I don't
get it. The angel comes and says,
"Listen, Daniel, let me give you
understanding."
that time
period that that sanctuary, we're
talking about a different sanctuary
because a sanctuary that you're thinking
of, that sanctuary is going to be
destroyed by the end of the 70 weeks.
But this vision goes beyond the 70
weeks. Therefore, the sanctuary that
you're thinking, all this is going to
happen with the earthly sanctuary, the
angel is saying, "No, no, no. I need you
to see this is going to deal with
another sanctuary that the Messiah
himself will
anoint. This will not be an earthly
temple, Daniel.
The time period points to a temple that
will not be that will a temple that is
not the one that will be standing that
was standing when Jesus
came. All right. So, who's the little
horn then? Come on. Let's let's we're
not finished. Are y'all good? Let's keep
moving. So, the question is, who then is
this little horn of Daniel chapter 8?
Because that's an objection as well. So
we know that the metopers uh is the ram.
We know that the hegoat is Greece. And
then we know that four horns came out of
the hegoat. And those horns were
represented by the four kingdoms under
Talamy, Salucid, Cassander, and Lemicus.
So the prophecy says in Daniel 8,
therefore the hegoat waxed very great,
and when he was strong, the great horn
was broken. That's Alexander the Great.
And for it came up four notable ones
toward the four winds of heaven. And
then it says these words, "And out of
one of them came forth a little horn
which waxed exceeding great toward the
south and toward the east and toward the
pleasant
land." So here's a question you guys. Is
this little horn of Daniel 8 the same
little horn of Daniel chapter 7? It
would seem that this is this would be
logical, but there's something that
throws people off because this little
horn is said to
rise out
of the Grecian
Empire. So, so for example, in Daniel 2,
we know that we have Babylon, me,
Persia, Greece, Rome. In Daniel 7, we
have Babylon, me, Persia, Greece, Rome.
In Daniel 8, there's no Babylon. starts
with me Persia. Then we have Greece. We
have the four horns. And then the
question is who? Who is that little horn
power that comes after the four horns of
Greece? Is it a Greek power or is it a
Roman power like we just saw in Daniel
chapter 7 and Daniel chapter 2?
Is it Antiochus
Epiphanies or is it something much
greater?
Well, let me just read something to
you and hopefully this will click once I
read it. I'm not going to say much. I'm
just going to read. Are y'all
ready? Here we go. By the way, by the
way, before we read before we read,
let's let's come back. Before we read,
hopefully y'all didn't see that cuz I
need y'all to No, no, no, no, no, no.
Don't go. Good, good, good, good, good.
So, if this little horn is Antiochus
Epiphies, please understand that Daniel
8 takes a nose dive when it comes to the
climax of the chapter. It just takes a
straight nose dive because now we're
concluding Daniel 8 with something that
happened in 164 BC with Antiochus
Epiphanies, you know, um making
some little moment of persecution
against the Jews and it ends right
there which would be very
antilimactic. So the only other option
is that it's
Rome. Just like Daniel 2, just like
Daniel 7, it's Rome. But how can you say
that Rome rose out of Greece? So let's
let's read something here. Ready? Let's
go to the screen. Let's go to the
screen. The Greco Roman
Empire. A fusion of Greek and Roman
cultures that significantly shaped
Western civilization, influencing art,
philosophy, politics, and law. The Greco
Ro the Greco Roman. Are y'all catching
this? The Greco Roman civilization
emerged from the cultural and political
interactions between ancient Greece and
Rome. This
blending, this
blending
began in the 2n century BC when the
Romans conquered Greeks. Conquered
Greece. While the Romans were militarily
dominant, they deeply admired Greek
culture, leading to a significant
cultural exchange that shaped both
societies. Y'all heard of Greor Roman
world? Greor Roman culture. Gre Greo
Roman Empire. Let me read another one.
Let me read another
one. Here we
go. Rome's Rome slowly overtakes Greece
after the Battle of Corinth. uh after
the battle of Corinth was just the
beginning. Rome's conquest of Corinth
did not lead to complete denomin uh
complete domination of Greece
immediately. Greece was divided into
republics which were then placed under
the control of Roman Senate. The
republics were eventually united and the
A the A the Aan league uh a loose
organization of northern states. This
opened the door to to further victories
over the rest of the Greek peninsula.
After first invading Macedonia, the
northernmost territory, a Roman
province, Rome took its time. Instead of
conquering, the conquerors methodically
extended power over Greek cities through
diplomacy and war. By 27 BC, the
conquest was complete when Augustus
Caesar made the entire Greek peninsula
the province of Aaya. Let me keep
reading.
What is interesting what is interesting
is that the Rome is that after Rome
conquered Greece, it is actually the
Greek culture that influenced the Roman
one. Usually, it's the other way around.
Nations defeat, nations defeated. The
Greek uh the Greek culture deeply
influenced the Romans in many ways.
First, Greek construction and
architecture influenced the Romans. The
Romans took the Greek column styles of
Doric, ionic and cor and Corinthian and
added their own style. The emperors
Caesar Augustus rebuilt Athens with the
construction of the Rome of the Roman
agora. A large concert hall called the
Agrippa was built in 15 BC, etc., etc.
Oh, so here we go. Wealthy Romans sought
Greek tutors to teach their children.
The literature and learning of Greece
also influenced Roman scholars of the
time. For example, Virgil was inspired
by the tales of Homer to write his
amiadid. Finally, the Greek language
influenced the Romans. The Romans
adopted the Greek culture, the Greek
alphabet and changed it from Latin,
which is the basis of many languages
that exist today. Greece, listen to this
y'all. Greek became the trade language
that united the the empire. All of the
influences prompted Horus, the Roman
poet, to conclude, watch
this, captive Greece took captive her
conqueror. All these articles are going
to be in my slides that you will have
access to. So, there are the sources and
I just want I'm gonna read through these
very quickly.
uh Rome rules through the collapse of
the Seucid Empire. So remember there
were four empires the Seucid, Talamy, uh
Lemicus and Cassander. The Salut the
Seucid Empire was the dominant eastern
Greek power. After Alexander's death,
his empire split into four horns
including the Seucids in the east. The
Seucid Empire ruled a vast region from
Syria to Per to Persia, controlling much
of the former Persian Empire. Watch
this. Rome's entry into the eastern
Mediterranean accelerated during the
Syrian war in which they defeated
Antiochus 3, the Seucid king. The Treaty
of Apa stripped the slle of their
western territories. Asia Minor went to
Rome's went to Rome's allies. A lot of
history here, but just follow along.
Rome, listen to this.
Rome. According to Daniel 8:9, one of
them came forth a little horn, which it
waxed exceeding great toward the south,
that would be Egypt, toward the east,
the Seucid Empire, and toward the
pleasant land, that is Rome.
Rome fits the
description of this little
horn that waxes great that instead of
overthrowing Greece, merged almost as it
were merged and came
up slowly conquering Greek territory
through diplomacy and war.
So note with
me, and it waxed great even to the host
of heaven, and it cast on some of the
host of the stars to the ground and
stamped upon them. Yay, he magnified
himself even to the prince of the host.
And by him the daily sacrifice was taken
away, and the place of his sanctuary was
cast down. How do these verses fulfill?
Well, let me read on. And a host was
given him against the daily sacrifice by
reason of transgression. It cast down
the truth to the ground. It practiced
and it prospered. So note with me please
note how both pagan Rome and paple Rome
which are both the little horn the
little horn is pagan Rome in its pagan
phase and then paple Rome they both did
the same
thing. No Rome is not the pleasant land
Judea was the pleasant land and Rome
conquered Judea. It it it waxed great
towards the pleasant land. So note
this, the little horn wax great to the
host of heaven. This was fulfilled by
pagan Rome in their persecution of of
Jews and Christians. It was fulfilled by
papal Rome during the dark ages.
Magnified himself to the prince of the
host. It was pagan Rome that crucified
Christ and it was papal Rome that rec
replaced Christ with popes and priests.
The daily was taken away. It was pagan
Rome that destroyed the literal temple
and it was papal Rome that obscured the
priesthood of the heavenly temple. Cast
a sanctuary down. That was done by pagan
Rome in in 70 AD. It was done by papal
Rome by replacing the heavenly ministry
with an earthly one. Cast the truth down
to the ground. That was done by pagan
Rome in its pagan phase persecuting
Christians. It was done by papal Rome
through doctrinal corruption and church
traditions practiced and prospered. That
was done by Rome's empire having a
global reach. That was done by papal
Rome in its papal dominance. In other
words,
beloved, Antiochus Epiphanies never cast
a sanctuary down. Did not dominate for
2,300 years. Not even 2,300 days.
Antiochus Epiphanies cannot be the
little horn of Daniel 8 because it is
antilimactic. So
then we're about to wrap this message up
you guys. But
here,
here is the most beautiful thing that I
hope you will ever hear about this
teaching that is found in Daniel 8:14.
Are y'all ready for this? We're about to
end the sermon, but really the sermon is
about to begin.
So, so far we have
seen that all the prophecies of Daniel,
Daniel 2, 7,9 and 12 all culminate with
the second coming of Christ. Daniel 8
should be no different. We have seen
that the question asked in Daniel 8 is
how long shall be the vision? The vision
spans from the Meo Persian Empire. It
spans through Greece and now we see it
spans through Rome all the way to papal
Rome which means that the 2300 years
must
conclude
sometime
after this this reign of the papal
Rome. Okay, we saw that the 2300 years
must be 2,300 days must be years because
they span the entire vision. We see that
in Daniel chapter 9. It is in fact an
answer to Daniel chapter 8. Why? Because
Daniel is confused about the time
element. There's not even a sanctuary
standing. How can the all this stuff be
happening with a temple that's not yet
standing? So the angel comes to explain
to him and says no 70 weeks will be
revolving around the sanctuary that will
be rebuilt but the remainder of it is
going to be another sanctuary one that
is one that will be anointed by Jesus
the Messiah
himself. We've seen then we've also seen
that the little horn that rises out or
that rises in Daniel 8 is the very same
little horn of Daniel 7. In Daniel 7,
the little horn is just the papacy. But
the p but in Daniel 7, the little horn
is on the fourth beast which is pagan
Rome. So Daniel 8 takes the little horn
symbol and
combines the beast and the horns of
Daniel 7. The little horn of Daniel 8 is
simply one symbol being used to describe
Rome in its pagan phase and then Rome in
its papal
phase. The little horn is chosen because
the message is designed to lead us not
to think so much about pagan Rome as it
is to focus upon papal
Rome. And now, and now
comes the
bombshell. So remember back in Daniel
8:2, come with me. Daniel 8:2, "And I
saw in vision, and it came to pass when
I saw that I was at Shushan in the
palace, which is in the province of
Elum, and I saw in a vision, and I was
by the river Eli." Why does God take
Daniel into a
kingdom that is not yet
standing? Come on.
So,
Shushan is
mentioned 21 times in the
Bible. One of those 21 times, we're not
going to go to the screen yet, just come
back for a moment. One of those times is
in Daniel 8:2. The other time, which we
read earlier, was in Nehemiah 1 verse
one.
The next the other 19
times that Shusan is
mentioned is in the book of Esther.
Y'all put that word in. Put that name in
the chat for me. Please put that book in
the chat for me, please. The book of
Esther.
Why is the palace of
Shushan mentioned in the book
of
Esther? And my bad. Did I say did I say
uh Greece
earlier? Did I say Greece
earlier? I think I said Greece
earlier. It is Meo Persia.
It is me
Persia. The book of
Esther mentions the palace of
Susan 19
times. Come on, let's go to the screen.
Let's go to the screen. Please note with
me Esther chapter 1 verse two that in
those days when the king
Ahazerus sat on his throne which was in
Shushan the
palace. Do y'all see this?
The king
Ahazerus sat on his
throne, the throne of his kingdom which
was in
Shushan the palace.
Why is God bringing our
attention to the future place, the
future kingdom, the future
capital of the
kingdom
where a very specific
event takes place in this palace.
Y'all go ahead and put a 10 in the chat
if you see if you see
what's
coming. Let's go to the
screen. How many of you know the story?
You know the story of of Esther? So, um,
in fact, no, no, no. Let's come back.
Let's come back. Let's come back. In the
book of Esther, um you have uh a guy by
the name of Hmon. Yes, remember Hmon.
And you have a woman by the name of
Esther. And you have King Asherus. And
then you have
Mori. And early on in the story, you'll
remember that there's a plot to kill the
king. And
Mori foils the plot. He foils the plot.
And
so when when when Morai falls apart,
note with me, Esther chapter 2:23, note
with me, um, and when inquisition was
made of the matter, it was found out,
therefore they were both hanged on a
tree, and it was written in the book of
Chronicles before the king. So then
watch this you guys in this story in
this event that is going to happen in
the palace of Shushan where the king
sits Mori who had saved the king's life
has his
deeds please write that out for me his
deeds are
written in a
book you all can go ahead
Go ahead and if you'd like to go ahead
and put a 10 in the chat, go ahead and
put a 10 in the chat. His deeds are
written in a book. Now, the story does
not end there, of course. What else
happens? Uh there's a man by the name of
Hmon. And Hmon um is angry because Mori,
you remember the story, refused to bow
to Hmon. So, Hmon wants to kill all the
Jews. So, what's going to happen is
there's going to be a death decree
issued. There's going to be a death
decree issued. And notice what it says
here. And Hmon said unto King Azerus,
"There is a certain people scattered
abroad and dispersed among the people in
all of the provinces of that kingdom.
And their laws are diverse from all
people. Neither keep they the king's
law. Therefore, it is for the king's
profit. It is not for the king's prophet
to suffer them. If it please a king, let
it be written that they may be
destroyed, and I will pay 10,000 talons
of silver to the hands of those that
have the charge of the business to bring
into the king's treasuries. So, there's
a death decree. Why is there a death
decree being issued? There's a death
decree being issued because of a people.
Because Hmon wants to destroy a people
who
keep laws that are
different from the laws of that
kingdom. These guys are commandment
keepers. They keep God's law. There
ought to be a death decree to wipe them
out. Are y'all following so far? All of
this beloved is happening at
Shushan. So Mori's deeds have been
written in a book. There is a death
decree. You all remember yall remember
uh that that uh in in fact check this
out. So how do they decide what day they
are going to destroy the Jews? Does
anyone remember? We're not going to put
this on the screen yet. Does anyone
remember in this story, how do they
decide when they're going to carry out
this death
decree? When they're going to carry out
this
annihilation, what do they do? They did
something. Anybody knows how they fell
upon the day in which they decided,
"This is when we're going to wipe out
the
Jews." All right.
So, let's go to the
screen. Let's go to the screen. Um, in
fact, let's go back here. A date was
chosen by casting
lots. A date was chosen by casting lots.
So remember how we said when Hmon saw
that Mordei bowed not nor did he
reverence then Hmon was full of wrath.
The dragon was angry full of wrath and
thought to scorn to lay hands on Mordei
alone for they shued him the people of
Mori. And wherefore Hmon sought to
destroy all the Jews that were
throughout the kingdom of Azerus even
the people of Mori. We couldn't get M I
couldn't get Mori to bow. Couldn't get
Jesus to bow. So I'm angry. I'm going to
go after I couldn't destroy Jesus. I'm
angry. I'm going to go after his
people. This is exactly what's happening
here, you guys. This is exactly what's
going on here. Watch this. Watch this.
So, in the first month, that is the
month of N N N N N N N N N N N N N N N N
N N N N N N N N N N N N N N N N N N N N
N N N Nissan, in the 12th year of the
king Asherus, they cast purr, that is
the lot before Hmon from day to day and
from month to month to the 12 month that
is the month of Ada. The reason they
were casting lots, the reason they were
casting lots was to decide. Listen
y'all, they were casting lots. Do lots
bring anything to your mind? The idea of
lots and um and books and and uh
decrees. Does does any of this bring
anything to your mind?
The Bible says in Revelation 12:17, "The
dragon was wroth with the woman and went
to make war with the remnant of her seed
which keep the commandments of God and
have the testimony of Jesus." These
people don't keep our laws, they ought
to be put to death. But hold on, hold
on, hold on. Watch this, you guys. So
watch what happens. If it please a king,
so we know that there's uh, you know,
he's going to pay talents. And the king
took his ring from his hand, and gave it
unto Hmon, the son of uh Hamdatha, the
Agite, the Jews enemy. And the king said
unto Hmon, "The silver is given to thee.
The people also do with thee, as it
seemed good." Then there were the king
scribes called on the 13th day of the
first month. And there was written
according to all that Hmon had
commanded, unto the king's lieutenants,
and to the governors that were over
every province, and to the rulers of
every people of every province,
according to the writing. And the king
sealed it with his ring. There's a seal.
There's there's there's a death decree.
There are lots. I need y'all to
understand what's going on here,
beloved. Because if you're like, "Hm,
all of this sounds familiar. All of this
books and and and lots and and and a
judgment and keeping the commandments of
God and a death decree." Hold on, you
guys. Could it be that Shan is a p? The
reason why God put Daniel in the palace
of Shusan before the events of Shusan
took place was that God was showing
Daniel this is what Daniel chapter 8 is
going to revolve around.
Not only will the prophecy begin with
the decree where the people of God are
keeping the commandments, where
judgment, where judges are set in place,
a and where the laws of God are brought
together, and where the people come out
of Babylon. But but in the very place
that you're having this vision,
something will unfold that will give you
insight into what I
mean by this little horn attacking the
people of God and seeking to destroy the
people of God. But somehow God is going
to intervene and reverse stuff and re
and Could it be
beloved? Could it be? Come back with me
to Esther 4:13. Mori commanded Esther,
"Think not to say to thyself that thou
shalt escape the king's house more than
all the Jews. Uh for if thou altogether
holdeth that th holdeth thy peace at
this time, then shall their enlargement
and deliverance arise to the Jews from
another place. But thou and thy father's
house shall be destroyed. And who knows
whether thou art come to the kingdom for
such a time as this. Watch this. Verse
15. Then Esther bade them return Mori
this answer. Go gather all the Jews that
are present in Shushan and fast for me.
And neither eat nor drink three days nor
nights. I also and my maidens will
likewise fast and I will go in unto the
king which is not according to the law
and if I perish I perish.
Esther goes in before the king the inner
chambers of the
king to
intercede on behalf of her
people. Why does God have Daniel? Why of
God put Daniel in the palace of Shushan
for this vision?
It is interesting that in Daniel 7:3 and
14, the Bible says, "I saw in visions by
night, and behold, one like the son of
man came with the clouds of heaven and
came to the ancient of days, and they
brought him near before him, and there
was given him dominion and glory and
power, h a kingdom that all peoples and
nations should serve him." This,
beloved, in Daniel 7 is a vision of
Christ entering into some place to stand
before the king and to receive a people,
to save a people. What does that have to
do with the little horn? What does that
have to do with the little Hmon, the
little horn? I'm sorry. What does that
have to do on that night? Watch this.
So, the night the night that that that
that that the king gives this command,
the Bible says on that night, the king
could not sleep.
And he commanded to bring the book of
records of the chronicles. And they were
read before the king. And it was found
written that Mori had told Big Dana and
Terish, two of the king's chamberlains,
the keepers of the doors, who sought to
lay hand on the king Ahazurus.
How is King Azerus going to be looking
at books, reviewing books? Come on
y'all. I'm not going to ask for a 10 in
the chat. I'mma ask for a 20 in the
chat. If you are
catching the massive
significance of what is going on right
now,
Azurus opens the
books and reviews the deeds of the
righteous. And it is that review of the
deeds of the righteous that will reverse
what the little horn had planned. I'm
sorry. What Hmon had planned, it will
reverse people talking about they're
afraid of the judgment. Listen to me,
you
guys. It is the review of the
books that is in favor of God's people.
Daniel 7:9 and 10. I beheld till thrones
were cast down and the ancient of days
did sit whose garment was white as snow
and the hair of his head like the pure
wool. His throne was like the fiery
flame and his wheels as burning
fire. A fiery stream issued and came
forth from before him. Thousand
thousands ministered unto him and 10,000
times 10,000 stood before him. The
judgment was set and the books were
opened.
Why does God bring Daniel into the
palace of Shushan, which is most likely
not even standing when Daniel has his
vision? Why does God supernaturally take
Daniel into this place, this palace of
the future king Ahazurus where he's
going to open books and review
characters and review deeds and
overturn? Why? All because of the
intercession of this woman who goes in
on behalf of her
people to intercede on their behalf.
Esther chapter 6:3-5. We're almost done,
y'all. We are almost done. And the king
said, "What honor and dignity has been
done to Mori for this?" Then said the
king's servants that ministered unto
him, "There is nothing done for him."
And the king said, "Who is in the
court?" Now Hmon was coming to the
outward court of the king's house to
speak unto the king to hang Morortei on
the gallows that he had prepared for
him. And the king's servant said unto
him, "Behold, Hmon standeth in the
court." And the king said, "Let him come
in." And y'all know the rest of the
story. The king said unto Azeras, or the
king Azarus said unto, "Let me pause.
Let me pause. Come back. Let's let's
let's get off the screen."
So the judgment reverses what was going
to happen to Mori. Morortei is blessed
instead of killed. And then Esther
reveals the plot of Hmon to the king.
And I want you to watch what happens in
verse chapter 7 5 and 6. Then King
Azerus answered and said unto Esther the
queen, "Who is he and where is he that
dur presume in his heart to do so?" And
Esther said, "The adversary,
Satan, the adversary and an enemy is
this wicked Hmon." Then Hmon was afraid
before the king and the queen. And y'all
know what happens next,
right? Do you do you guys know what
happens
next? What happens
next is that Hmon is killed.
Why is this so
interesting? In Leviticus 16 7 and 8,
talking about the day of atonement, the
day of judgment, there were lots
cast. There were lots that were cast in
Leviticus 16:7. The Bible says, "And he
shall take the two goats and present
them before the Lord at the door of the
tabernacle of the congregation. And
Aaron shall cast lots upon the two
goats, one lot for the Lord
Mori. One lot for the Lord and the other
lot for the
skategoats. Yes, you
are. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
See, when these lots are cast, the the
the thing that was supposed to destroy
Mori ended up destroying
Hmon. This is what the judgment does,
you
guys. In this on the day of atonement,
two lots were cast. one for the Lord,
the other for the scapegoat. The
scapegoat will ultimately
suffer and ultimately be
punished because of the judgment.
In other words, beloved, the story of
Esther, the story of what happened in
the palace at
Shushan has
direct relevance to what is happening in
Daniel chapter
8. A king on a throne with books, a
judgment, lots being
cast, the
reversal, the
reversal of that which was meant to
destroy God's people now being the means
by which they are delivered.
And this is where the Jews established
the feast of Purim, the celebration of
Purim. Let's go to the screen. We're
almost done here. We got just a few more
slides. This verse records the
establishment of the f of the feast of
Purim, commemorating the Jews
deliverance from Hmon's plot of
extermination. The celebration was
instituted as an annual memorial to
remind future generations of God's
providential care. After the dramatic
reversal of fortune where Hmon was
executed on the very gallows he had
prepared for Morai, the Jews were
granted permission by King Azerus to
defend themselves against their enemies.
Their victory over those who sought to
destroy them transformed the days
intended for their destruction into days
of triumph.
So many of us see the judgment of God as
a thing that is supposed to destroy us.
When beloved, it is a thing that is
designed to deliver us from the
enemy. Come on
y'all. The name Purum comes from the
Persian word purr, meaning lot. It's on
the screen. Referring to how Hmon had
cast lots to determine the day for
destroying the Jews. What began as a
scheme for annihilation became a
celebration of deliverance marked by
four key elements. One, feasting
together in communal joy. Two, sending
gifts of food. Three, giving charable.
Four, reading the story of Esther. This
joyous festival continues to be
celebrated by the Jews worldwide. It is
a reminder of God's protective hand over
his people. Beloved, the judgment is
about God's vindication of his people.
Note the parallels. a death decree in
the end times paralleling a a judgment
based on records on books in Daniel
chapter 7. Intercession by a mediator
Esther as a type of
Christ. Condemnation of the wicked,
vindication of the
righteous. Come on
y'all. The feast of Purum originates
from the events of Shashan. And pure is
a celebration of deliverance and
reversal of fate from condemnation to
redemption. This resonates with the
cleansing of the sanctuary in Daniel
8:14. A restoration of truth,
vindication of God's people, and a
public reversal of Satan's
accusation. Come on,
y'all. So, what are the parallels? God,
the king, examines the record books.
Jesus, the intercessor, plead for his
people. Satan the accuser is ultimately
expo exposed and the righteous are
vindicated and the wicked
condemned. You cannot make this stuff up
y'all. What are the parallels in the
book of
Esther? Royal throne and laws
intercession by Ether Esther. Book of
records uh Hmon accused vindication of
Mori. Death decree reversed. Beloved,
listen.
What more is there to
say? How in the world? How in the world
can we
say that Daniel 8 was
fulfilled in Antiochus
Epiphanies, which much of the world
don't even know who that
is, what he did? How in the world can
the grand
scheme of the book of
Daniel How in the world can the grand
scheme of the book of Daniel just
suddenly disappear off the page in
Daniel chapter 8? How can that
be? How can it be that there are
literally thousands of ways to prove
what Daniel chapter 8 is referring to?
And yet people want to say that's not in
the Bible. Where did you get that
from? How?
How? What did we just do? We just stayed
in the book of Daniel. That's all we
did. We just said, "Hey, we're going to
take all our cues from the book of
Daniel. We're going to look at the
themes of the chapters. We're gonna see
that they're all they all span thousands
of years. They all culminate in a grand
theme of judgment of the second coming
of
Jesus. The angel literally asks how long
is the
vision? The vision exps me Persia,
Greece, Rome, paple Rome. How can 2300
days be days and not years? We've seen
Daniel 9 as an answer to Daniel 8. We've
seen Daniel 9 was to clarify what what
Daniel was thinking about Daniel 8. No,
no, no. This is not a earthly temple.
This is a heavenly sanctuary. We've seen
that shushet. We've seen the little horn
cannot be Antioch's epiphanies. We've
seen this Greco Roman rise to power with
Rome ultimately conquering all of
Greece. Not like Babylon, not like meers
did Babylon. Not like Greece did me.
Rome took time and and blended in with
Greece to come into power. And then
we've seen that beautiful key of why God
has Daniel in
Shushan. Beloved, the truth of God's
word is unassalable.
if you will only accept
it and not bring well it can't be true
because the majority of people don't
think this it can't be true because this
it can't be true oh this this teaching
just came from you know this this extra
biblical prophet or this teaching just
came from from Ellen White and without
Ellen White you can't you can't you
can't without really you
guys this is this is Bible all day this
This is all we've done. Bible. No
commentators. No, just Bible and
history. Heavenly
Father, thank you for
speaking. Open our
eyes and help us to trust
truth. Help us to believe
truth. Help us to follow
truth. Thank you Lord for speaking.
Thank you for teaching us
today. In Jesus name we pray.
Amen. I'm going to invite you all to the
uh afterlow. We're going to put the link
in the chat. Uh the afterglow is no
longer on Altar Live. It is going to be
on Mighty Networks. And so um uh please
go ahead and put it in the chat. By the
way, let me put up
um let me put up this closing slide. So,
if you want to get uh access uh you can
either connect on our social media um
prayer request, you'll see it up there
as well. And I believe that there should
be nope there is no uh link for these
sermons or for these for these slides
but um there will be a link put up uh on
under under the link in the YouTube
channel on living mana uh as well as
probably our mighty network. So with
that said guys may God bless you. Thank
you for hanging in there with me today.
I know today we went longer than usual
but I told you today was going to be a
study not so much a sermon. And um
again, may God bless you, may God keep
you, and uh may God continue to guide
you into all truth.
Amen. Thank you for joining us today. If
this is your first time worshiping with
us, please check out our website at
livingmana.urch. We are not just here
for Sabbath service. We have weekly
programming too that covers mental
health, physical health, weekly prayer
service, financial health, and proving
the existence of God. It is our desire
that our programming will continue to
bless you. Please continue to pray for
us as we fulfill God's mission to go
into all the world with the gospel of
Jesus Christ.
[Music]